Guide to the Laura Stedman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Laura Stedman Papers
1887-1931
1894-1926
YCAL MSS 291
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.43
(15 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and personal papers which document the personal and professional life of Laura Stedman. The correspondence highlights personal and professional affiliations with Edmund Clarence Stedman (grandfather), Dr. George M. Gould (husband), and a number of writers including Martha Dickinson Bianchi, Ednah Proctor Clarke (Hayes), and Cora Miranda Baggerly Older. The papers include examples of Stedman's writing, publications, and a run of her scrapbook journals.
Stedman, Laura, 1881-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Milton Seabury Dees, 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biography
Laura Woodworth Stedman was born in 1881, the daughter of Frederick Stuart Stedman and Ellen Montague Douglas Stedman, and the granddaughter of banker, editor, and poet, Edmund Clarence Stedman. She was educated at private schools in New York City, including Arundell Academy and the Brackett School. Stedman served as literary secretary to her grandfather in the decade preceding his death in 1908 and, thereafter, as his literary executor. In 1908 Stedman contributed a bibliography to George M. Gould's Concerning Lafcadio Hearn. Working with Gould again, she edited a two-volume edition of her grandfather's letters, Life and Letters of Edmund Clarence Stedman (1910). In 1916 she published a short appreciation of Bayard Taylor in The Mid-West Quarterly. The following year Stedman and Gould married, taking up residence in Atlantic City, New Jersey. After Gould's death in 1922, Stedman remained in Atlantic City through 1930, in which census she is listed as a widow and an author. At the time of her death in 1939, Stedman was married to Milton Seabury Dees and resided in New York.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and personal papers that document the personal and professional life of Laura Stedman. The correspondence constitutes the larger part of the collection and highlights personal and professional affiliations with Edmund Clarence Stedman (grandfather), Dr. George M. Gould (husband), Ellen Douglas Stedman (mother), and a number of writers including Martha Dickinson Bianchi and Cora Miranda Baggerly Older. Of particular note is the correspondence group related to her work as literary agent for the writer Ednah Proctor Clarke (Hayes), which includes correspondence, playscripts, and contractual agreements between a range of interested parties including the actress Khyva St. Albans and a number of theatrical producers. Writings include notes and a typescript for a play titled "The Conquering Flame," notes and correspondence related to the editing and publication of the letters and manuscripts of Edmund Clarence Stedman, and limited collected writings of other authors, including Mary S. Edgar. The personal papers include materials related to Stedman's education, including an early report card and school notebooks; a run of scrapbook journals containing notes, photographs, postcards, and clippings which document a range of interests; and collected visual materials including drawings attributed to Albert Bierstadt and Petrella da Bologna.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1887-1930; II. Writings, circa 1902-1928. III. Personal papers, 1888-1931.
Related Materials
Edmund Clarence Stedman Collection, YCAL MSS 1008.
American literature -- 20th Century; Bianchi, Martha Dickinson, 1866-1943; Clarke, Ednah Proctor; Gould, George M. (George Milbry), 1848-1922; Older, Fremont, Mrs., 1875-1968; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Stedman, Laura, 1881-1939
- Correspondence, 1887-1930; Series I
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is organized into three subseries: General, Personal, and Professional.
  General and personal correspondence are arranged alphabetically by name; professional correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence of Laura Stedman. The General and Personal correspondence include similar material, but the Personal correspondence is comprised of more extensive exchanges with family and friends that were previously separated out by Stedman and library staff. Professional correspondence includes correspondence related to her work as a writer, editor, and literary agent as well as voluntary efforts related to World War I.
  - General correspondence
    General correspondence is comprised of incoming correspondence.
    - A, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Albee, John and Helen R. Albee, 1887-1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alden, Henry Mills, 1911 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aldrich, Thomas Bailey, [No year] Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B, 1905-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bacheller, Irving, 1909 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1908 Aug 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - C, 1908-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Coates, Florence Earle, 1907-1917 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cortissoz, Royal, 1916-1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cushing, Harvey, 1922 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - D, 1906-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Damrosch, Walter, 1919 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dwight, Timothy, 1900 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - E-F, 1906-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Furness, Horace Howard, 1912 Jan 28-1912 Apr 12, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - G, 1915-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Gates, Eleanor, 1914 Feb 26-1914 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Gilder, Jeannette Leonard, 1909 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Gould, George M. (George Milbry), 1917 Oct 5-29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Travel correspondence addressed to Ellen Douglas Stedman and "Boy Douglas" (probably a dog).
    - H, 1905-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Holt, Henry, 1923 Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Howe, M. A. De Wolfe (Mark Antony De Wolfe), 1923 Feb 16-Apr 5 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Howells, Mildred, 1922 Nov 12 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Hutton, Laurence, 1900 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - I-K, 1905-1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Janvier, Catharine A. (Ann) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Janvier, Thomas Allibone, 1903 Jan 27-1907 Dec 25 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Jenks, Tudor, 1911 Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1908 Oct 7-1925 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - L, 1906-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Lang, Leonora Blanche, 1912 Sep 24-27 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - LeMoyne, Sarah Cowell, 1905 Dec 27-1908 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - M-N, 1901-1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - MacKaye, Percy, 1904 Nov 11-1912 Jul 6 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - MacManus, Catalina Violante Páez, 1908 Jul 20-Sep 25, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - MacManus, Seamus, 1907 May 19-1917 Oct 12 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
      Includes correspondence addressed to Laura Stedman and Ellen Douglas Stedman (mother).
    - Matthews, Brander, 1914 Jan 10-14 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Moore, Victor, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Mosher, Thomas Bird, 1913 Jan 30-1914 Apr 18 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - P, 1911-1921, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Peabody, Josephine Preston, 1901 Jan 4-May 6 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - R, 1903-1922, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - S, 1903-1929, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Sharp, Elizabeth A. (Elizabeth Amelia), 1910 Oct 23, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Sharp, William, 1905 Oct 15-1905 Feb 5 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Sinclair, Upton, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Includes correspondence addressed to Edmund Clarence Stedman and Laura Stedman
    - Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1902 Jul 31-1905 Sep 3 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Stone, Ella B., 1905 Dec 23-1919 Apr 22 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - T, 1905-1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Tabb, John B. (John Banister), 1899 Oct 4 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Torrence, Ridgely, 1900 Sep 18-1917 Nov 27 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - V-Z, 1899-1924, undated (Box 3, Folder 54-55)
    - Vanamee, Grace Davis and Franklin Purdy Crasto, Jr., 1922 Sep 16-1930 Jun, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Warren, Maude Radford, 1923 Jun 11-30 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - White, Andrew Dickson, 1909 Mar 29 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Whiting, Charles Goodrich, 1908 Apr 1-1910 Oct 12 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Wilson, Edna E., 1913 Aug 22-1925 Dec 22, undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Wilson, Francis, 1912 Apr 18-1916 Jun 2 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Winter, Elsie Leslie, 1906 Nov 8-1929 Dec, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Winter, Jefferson, 1908 Dec 7-1913 Dec 14, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Winter, William, 1909 Dec 31-1916 Dec 29, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Woodberry, George Edward, 1904 Oct 7 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Miscellaneous notes and holiday cards, 1919, undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Personal correspondence
    Personal correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence.
    - Alexeyeva, Ayenara, 1923-1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 67-69)
      Correspondence includes clippings and programs related to performances of Ayenara Alexeyeva and Holger Alexeyev-Mehner, single intaglio print by Jean de Paleologue (signed PAL).
    - Bianchi, Martha Dickinson, 1905-1918, undated (Box 5, Folder 70-73)
      Incoming correspondence addressed to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Ellen Douglas Stedman, and Laura Stedman.
    - Brower family, 1907-1928
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence between Laura Stedman and George M. Gould and members of the Brower family. The bulk of the material is comprised of correspondence between Laura Stedman (Gould) and Pauline Florence Brower.
      - Brower, Beatrice, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Brower, Farrand Dodd, 1922-1924, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Brower, Farrand Dodd, Jr., 1927-1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Brower, Pauline Florence, 1907-1910 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Brower, Pauline Florence, 1912-1922, undated (Box 6, Folder 78-88)
      - Crosby, Arvia Brower, 1923-1929, undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
        Correspondence, includes clippings and photographs.
      - Third party, 1923-1927, undated (Box 6, Folder 90)
        Miscellaneous third-party correspondence and notes related to Pauline Florence Brower and family.
    - Corrigan, Matthew Poole, 1923-1929 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - DeVere, Mary A., 1913-1919, undated (Box 7, Folder 92-93)
    - Douglas, George, Mrs. (grandmother), 1888 Feb 16 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Older, Cora Miranda Baggerly (Mrs. Fremont Older), 1906-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 95-98)
    - Redway, Jacques W. (Jacques Wardlaw), 1923-1930, undated (Box 8, Folder 99-101)
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence (grandfather), undated (Box 8, Folder 102)
      Material includes third-party correspondence addressed to Edmund Clarence Stedman.
    - Stedman, Ellen Montague (Douglas) (mother), 1893-1926 (Box 8, Folder 103-110)
      General note
      Outgoing correspondence, documenting travel, includes postcards.
    - Stedman, Frederick Stuart (father), 1900 Feb 19 (Box 8, Folder 111)
      Outgoing correspondence comprised of 1 autograph letter signed.
    - Stedman, Laura Hyde Woodworth (grandmother), 1888 (Box 8, Folder 112)
      4 autograph letters signed to Mrs. E. C. Stedman.
    - Watson, Edward Willard, 1914-1925 (Box 8, Folder 113-114)
      Correspondence includes drawings ("wiggles") and discussion of a Billy Sunday campaign (1918).
    - Watson, Edward Willard, 1914-1925 (Box 9, Folder 115-116)
    - Miscellaneous family and friends, circa 1925-1927 (Box 9, Folder 117-124)
      Miscellaneous correspondence with relatives and friends arranged by Laura Stedman according to year: 1925-1930. Though the bulk of the material falls within the given time period, the chronological arrangement is not strict and files frequently contain groupings from individual correspondents that vary from the ascribed date.
      Correspondents include: Helen R. Albee (Mrs. John Albee), Rebecca Baker, Marjory Bonar, Eleanor P. Clarke, Alpheus Geer, Mrs. S. A. B. Harvey, Jesse G. Hollingsworth, Elizabeth Dodge Huntington, John G. Kello, Evelyn Nichols Kerr, Marguerite Langdon Larned (Mrs. William Trowbridge Larned), Helen Marsh (Mrs. Edward C. Marsh), Harry Marshall (florist), Ada Sterling, Mathilde L. Thomas, Kathryn Davison Tulloch (Mrs. Rudolph Lang Tulloch), Rudolph Lang Tulloch, Josephine Griswold Wardlaw, Grace M. Warner, Herbert P. Whitlock.
    - Miscellaneous family and friends, circa 1929-1930 (Box 10, Folder 125-132)
  - Professional correspondence, 1899-1926
    - Library of American Literature, Edmund Clarence Stedman, ed., 1901-1926, undated (Box 10, Folder 133)
    - Literary agents and publishers, 1909-1917, undated (Box 10, Folder 134-136)
    - Literary representation of Ednah Proctor Clarke (Hayes), 1914-1924
      Correspondence concerning efforts to produce Ednah Proctor Clarke's play "The Chrysalis" (alternately identified as "The Judgment Seat"). Material includes playscript drafts, notes, contractual agreements, and third-party correspondence.
      - Clarke, Ednah Proctor, 1914-1924, undated (Box 11, Folder 137-142)
        Biographical/Historical note
        Mrs. Henry L. Hayes
      - Saenger, Nayán, 1916-1921, undated (Box 11, Folder 143-144)
      - St. Albans, Khyva, 1916-1919, undated (Box 11, Folder 145)
    - Professional affiliations and war work, 1917-1924 (Box 11, Folder 146)
- Writings, circa 1902-1928; Series II
  Writings are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - "The Conquering Flame", undated (Box 12, Folder 147)
    Notes and typescript for a play
  - Miscellaneous drafts, notes, clippings, and related correspondence, circa 1902-1928, undated (Box 12, Folder 148-150)
  - Notes for an edition of E. C. Stedman letters, undated (Box 12, Folder 151-153)
    Removed from his An American Anthology (1900), vols. 1-2
  - Writings of others
    - Edgar, Mary S.
      - "The Conspiracy of Spring", 1920 (Box 12, Folder 154)
      - "The Cryptomeria Tree", 1924 (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - Loti, Pierre, "India" from L'Inde (sans les Anglais), undated (Box 12, Folder 156)
      Unidentified translation of excerpts from text
- Personal papers, 1888-1931; Series III
  Series III is arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Report card, 1890 (Box 12, Folder 157)
  - Scrapbooks
    27 note-books, containing copies in her handwriting of various poems, together with postcards, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
    - 10 volumes, 1923 Jan-1927 Mar 25 (Box 13, Folder 158-168)
    - 11 volumes, circa 1927-1929 (Box 14, Folder 169-179)
    - 6 volumes, circa 1930-1931, undated (Box 15, Folder 180-185)
    - Loose clippings found with scrapbooks., undated (Box 15, Folder 186)
  - Student notebooks
    - English (3 vols.), circa 1894-1896 (Box 16, Folder 187)
    - History (1 vol.), 1894-1897 (Box 16, Folder 188)
  - Visual materials, undated
    - Bierstadt, Albert (attributed), watercolor drawings (butterfly), undated (Box 16, Folder 189)
    - Copy prints, undated (Box 16, Folder 190)
    - Petrella da Bologna, Vittorio (attributed), 5 charcoal drawings, undated
      Stored in: Oversize Petrella da Bologna, Vittorio, 5 charcoal drawings
  - Printed Ephemera, 1908-1919, undated (Box 16, Folder 191)
    Also stored in: Oversize, Printed ephemera
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1888-1908, undated (Box 16, Folder 192)
- Oversize, Series IV
  - Petrella da Bologna, Vittorio, 5 charcoal drawings, undated (Box 17, Folder 193-197)
  - Printed ephemera, 1902, 1919 (Box 17, Folder 198)